Hartford Gay and Lesbian Health Collective (HGLHC) Collection GLBTQ.2013.01
GLBTQ Archives
Hartford Gay and Lesbian Health Collective (HGLHC) Collection
1983-2010
GLBTQ.2013.01
Connecticut Polish American Archives
3.0 Linear feet
The Hartford Gay and Lesbian Health Collective began as the “Hartford Gay Health Collective” in 1983 as a place for gay men to obtain screenings for STDs and Hepatitis. HIV testing was added in 1986 as a response to the HIV/AIDS crisis. In 1987, services were expanded to include women, and the name was changed to the Hartford Gay and Lesbian Health Collective. Over the years, HGLHC has expanded to assumed responsibility for many gay, lesbian, bisexual, and transgender programs and services throughout the Hartford area, including the Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE festival.
Biographical/Historical note
The Hartford Gay and Lesbian Health Collective began as the “Hartford Gay Health Collective” in 1983 as a place for gay men to obtain screenings for STDs and Hepatitis. HIV testing was added in 1986 as a response to the HIV/AIDS crisis. In 1987, services were expanded to include women, and the name was changed to the Hartford Gay and Lesbian Health Collective.
HGLHC opened its first office on Broad Street in the Community Center in 1992. In 1996 it moved to its current location at 1841 Broad Street. Over the years, HGLHC has expanded to assumed responsibility for many gay, lesbian, bisexual, and transgender programs and services throughout the Hartford area. LGBT youth have a place to socialize at the “Rainbow Room” within the center. Social networking sites, blogs, and email announcements have been added to HGLHC’s expanding role in the community as internet services have expanded.
As the HIV/AIDS crisis became more and more prominent, HGLHC responded with additional health programs and advocacy involvement. Some of these include taking part in the Connecticut Gay Pride Parades and sponsoring or underwriting other gay and lesbian community groups and fundraising events. From 1992 through 1994, it took responsibility for the bookeeping of the Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE Festivals, and continued to plan the festival program booklets through 1999. Presence at political functions also increased over time. Evidence of the organization’s activism includes a wealth of news releases and letters in support of LGBT issues. The collective also developed its own fundraising events, the most well known being the “One Big Event”, produced each fall, and attracting local celebrities and dignitaries. Since HGLHC has been involved in a great many collaborations with other groups within the Gay and Lesbian Community in the Hartford area, "One Big Event" is very well attended.
In addition to in-house fundraising activities, HGLHC has received funding from a variety of organizations, including the Hartford Foundation for Public Giving, the Gill Foundation, the Center of Interdisciplinary Research at Yale, and the cities of Hartford and Manchester.
Scope and Contents note
The collection includes advertisements, annual reports, publicity, program flyers, correspondence, and documentation of various activities that helped to benefit the organization. The bulk of the material dates from the mid-1990’s to 2003. HGLHC's involvement with the Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE Festival is documented through planning and bookeeping files.
Conditions Governing Access note
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Arrangement note
The collection is divided into five series: I. Organizational Records (These also including flyers advertising programs and services) I.(a) Sponsorship of Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE Festival II. Advertising and publicity (Purchased advertisements and articles) III. Fundraising activities IV. Conferences & other activities V. Realia, and graphic materials
Several folders, donated by Linda Estabrook, with materials covering years 1990 -2004 were added in January 20014 to organizational records series.
Related Archival Materials note
Connecticut Gay and Lesbian PRIDE Festival (CGLPF) collection (GLBTQ.2013.02). Oral history interviews of Linda Estabrook, Albert Kissling and Robert Belliveau are available within the Digital Collections of the GLTBQ Archives on the website of Elihu Burritt Library.
Estabrook, Linda; Hartford Gay and Lesbian Health Collective.; AIDS (Disease) -- Prevention.; AIDS (Disease) -- Social aspects.; Community health services -- Connecticut; Gay community -- Connecticut; Gay pride parades; Gays -- Connecticut -- Exhibitions; Homosexuality and education -- Connecticut
- Publicity articles and advertisements, 1983-2010
  - Advertisements, 1990-1999 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Advertisements, 2000-2010 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Advertisements in Metroline (originals), 2000 (Box 2)
  - Articles about AIDS, 1990-1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Articles and letters to the editor from HGLHC personnel, 1996-2001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Articles about HGLHC, 1983-1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Articles about HGLHC, 1990-1999 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Articles about HGLHC, 2000-2010 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Crawford, Mallory. "An Open Letter...", December 11, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Estabrook, Linda (articles about, activities of), 1989-2006 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - LaFleur, Gary. "Many faces of the health collective", Metroline, January 1997., January 22-28, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Metroline (publicity, advertisements), 1990-1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Metroline (publicity and advertisements), 2000-2010 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Fundraising activities, 1990-2010
  - Connecticut AIDS Bike Tour (flyers), 2003-2008 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Carols of hope (information on cassette), undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Cabaret 1997 (program), January 24-26, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Gay bingo (flyers), 1990-2008 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Var La La La La at Hartford Stage, December 19, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Fundraising events (miscellaneous flyers), 1990-2008 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Gay pride, 1994-2001 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Tenth anniversary fundraiser concert (flyers), 1993 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - One big event, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - One big event, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - One big event, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - One big event, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - One big event, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - One big event, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - One big event, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - One big event copy of a US Patent and Trademark Office, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 29A)
  - New York City Pride Bus Trip, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Pride stride, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Snowball programs and news articles, 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Conferences and other activities
  - Artists against AIDS (program and article), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - AIDS in Connecticut: Resources, reports and programs, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - AIDS Project Hartford (programs and services), undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - CIRA Research -Yale (Summary), undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - The Connecticut Gay Men's Chorus (concert program), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Gay civil rights protests, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Gay community events, 1990-2000 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Gay men's health crisis (brochures), undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Greystone Insurance (brochure)`, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Hogar CREA International (program), 2001 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - House of Flava Butta' Ball (program), April 19, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - National Alliance of Breast Cancer Organizations (newsletters, articles, informational brochures), 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - 13th National Lesbian and Gay Health Conference, July 24-28, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - 14th National Lesbian and Gay Health Conference, July 8-12, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - 18th National Lesbian and Gay Health Conference, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - 19th National Lesbian and Gay Health Conference, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - National Health Council Advocacy Meeting, December 2-4, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Pa'fuera Pa'lante (program), September 26-28, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Promote the vote (community organizing guide), July, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Provisions (conference), 1993 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Provisions (conference), 1996 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Provisions IV: Living with HIV/AIDS (conference), June 7-9, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Provisions -- 1998, 2000 & 2002 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Technical Assistance Manual for Developing Feminist/Lesbian Cancer Projects, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Traumatic Stress Institute, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - True Colors XIV, March 23-24, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Resource Guides (True Colors and AIDS), 2007-2009 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - AIDS and HIV related health newsletters: "Positive Health News" report #7 1994; "Network News" January 1995; "LifeTimes" Winter 1991-92; "New England AIDS E.T.C. Newsline" Fall 1995; "CPS InfoPack" June 1993; "FOCUS" December 1991., 1991-1995 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - AIDS and HIV related health newsletters for the year 2000: "AIDS Action News" Spring 2000; "CPS InfoPack" Vol.10, No. 2, 2000; "HIV Network News" Winter/Spring 2000; "Needle Tips" Spring/Summer 2000; "Positives for Positives" Spring 2000 (Box 2, Folder 59)
- Realia and graphic materials
  - "One Big Event" (poster) (4 copies), November 5, 2005 (Box 3, Object 21)
  - "One Big Event" (poster), November 8, 2003 (Box 3, Object 40)
  - "Leading the Way Together" (poster), June 3-4, 1994 (Box 3, Object 20)
  - "One Big Event" (poster) (4 copies), November 13, 2004 (Box 3, Object 19)
  - "One Big Event" Silent Auction sign, November 13, 2004 (Box 3, Object 43)
  - "One Big Event" (poster, November 10, 2007 (Box 3, Object 42)
  - "One Big Event" (poster) (4 copies), November 4, 2006 (Box 3, Object 18)
  - "One Big Event" (poster), November 17, 2012 (Box 3, Object 44)
  - "TransHealth screening day" (poster) (3 copies), November 12, 2005 (Box 3, Object 17)
  - "women's health screening day" (poster), January 29, 2005 (Box 3, Object 16)
  - Hildebran, Gretchen, "Out in the Heartland" (VCR tape), undated (Box 3, Cassette 15)
  - Trenor, Maria, "With What Shall I Wash?" (VCR tape), undated (Box 3, Cassette 14)
  - Gilomen, Jen, "In My Shoes", undated (Box 3, Object 13)
  - "Outing Riley" (VCR tape), undated (Box 3, Cassette 12)
  - Hat with "she's OUT all night" logo, undated (Box 3, Object 11)
  - 5th Annual CT AIDS Bike Tours T-Shirt, undated (Box 3)
  - CT AIDS Bike tours T-Shirt, undated (Box 3, Object 9)
  - Gay and Lesbian voters for Clinton Gore T-Shirt, 1992 (Box 3, Object 8)
  - April Announcement flyer (3.5 inch floppy disk), undated (Box 3, Object 6)
  - DJW card size ad, undated (Box 3, Object 5)
  - HGLHC 25 years commemorative key ring, 2008 (Box 3, Object 3)
  - Gay pride sign for HGLHC (pink triangle on tongue depressor), undated (Box 3, Object 2)
  - CTAC TransHealth Reference (CD), 2005 (Box 3, Object 1)
  - Envelope containing variety of tickets and small paper items advertising various programs, undated (Box 3, Object 4)
  - 1993 Commemorative Invitation to the 52nd Presidential Inaugural (Box 3, Object 7)
  - Peabody studio pin. [20th Anniversary commemorative gift pin specially commissioned from glass artisan Dennis Peabody with Chinese symbols for Health], 2003 (Box 3, Object 22)
  - Peabody studio pin. [20th Anniversary commemorative gift pin specially commissioned from glass artisan Dennis Peabody], 2003 (Box 3, Object 23)
  - Peabody studio pin. [20th Anniversary commemorative gift pin specially commissioned from glass artisan Dennis Peabody], 2003 (Box 3, Object 24)
  - Peabody studio pin. [20th Anniversary commemorative gift pin specially commissioned from glass artisan Dennis Peabody], 2003 (Box 3, Object 25)
  - Peabody studio pin. [20th Anniversary commemorative gift pin specially commissioned from glass artisan Dennis Peabody], 2003 (Box 3, Object 26)
  - Peabody studio pin. [20th Anniversary commemorative gift pin specially commissioned from glass artisan Dennis Peabody], 2003 (Box 27, Object 27)
  - Tom's Cookies gift tag from the 52nd Presidential Inauguration, January 2993 (Box 3, Object 29)
  - Inauguration Day (pin), 1993 (Box 3, Object 30)
  - Candy bar wrapper from Inauguration Day, January 1993 (Bin 3, Object 28)
  - Gay & Lesbian voters for Clinton Gore (pin), 1992 (Box 3, Object 31)
  - Jefferonian Democracy (William Jefferson Clinton pin), 1992 (Box 3, Object 32)
  - Clinton Gore (political pin), 1992 (Box 3, Object 33)
  - 52nd Presidential Inauguration (pin), January 20, 1993 (Box 3, Object 34)
  - Pride (pin with pink triangle), 1992 (Box 3, Object 35)
  - Hartford Gay and Lesbian Health Collective (emory board), undated (Box 3, Object 36)
  - Hartford Gay and Lesbian Health Collective (emory board), undated (Box 3, Object 37)
  - 10th anniversary refrigerator magnet, 1993 (Box 3, Object 38)
  - 25th anniversary refrigerator magnet, 2008 (Box 3, Object 39)
  - The Hartford Gay and Lesbian Health Collective (Banner), undated (Oversize on shelf)
  - Faculty appreciation award for Mrs. Miller of HGLHC, 2008 (Box 3, Object 41)
  - Small cardboard box labeled "sundance" and inscribed, "To Frank Gagliardi From Linda Estabrook - Pins". Four pins were transferred to the GLBTQ Button collection (2013.04): "Artists Against Aids"; "NLGHA"; Unity 94; and an Angels in American pin designed by Milton Glaser. (Box 3, Object 45)
  - DVD: Connecticut AIDS Bike Tour, undated (Box 3)
  - DVD: Connecticut AIDS Bike Tour (PSA - 2 spots), undated (Box 3)
- Organizational records, 1983-2008
  - AIDS education request for proposals, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - AIDS leadership awards (program), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - AIDS leadership awards (programs), 1993-2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AIDS leadership awards (programs), 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual report, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual report, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual report, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual report, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Annual report, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual report, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Annual report, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual report, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual report, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Annual report, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Annual report, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Annual report, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Annual report, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Annual report, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Annual report, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Annual plan meeting (white binder), 2008 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Anonymous record form and HIV counseling guide and client record, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Awards (photocopies), 1994-2007 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Board minutes and memos, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Brochures, announcements and invitations, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Connecticut gay and lesbian film festival (sponsorship), 1995-2001 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence (email announcements), 2001-2008 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence (internal), 1997-2007 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence incoming, 1990-2000 (Box 1, Folder 28a)
  - Correspondence outgoing, 1991-2005 (Box 1, Folder 28b)
  - Donation requests (annual), 1996-2008 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Dorothy award, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Erotic choices (flyers), 1993-2000 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Evaluation surveys (forms), undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Executive committee meeting, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Flyers (miscellaneous), 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Flyers (miscellaneous), 2000-2010
  - Gay men (programs supporting health of), undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Gay men's health project, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Gay men's health summit, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Gay leadership council correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - HIV (programs about), undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Job postings, 2000-2006 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Jolin, Robert Edward, 1945-2001 (funeral program and biography of founder of HGLHC (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Latino/as contra SIDA (flyers and brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Leading the way together. Multicultural approach to GLB HIV/AIDS Prevention, June 3 and 4, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Lesbians (programs supporting health of), 1990-2003 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - LGBT sexual assault and domestic violence task force, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Living soulfully (flyers), undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Needs assessment survey findings, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Newsletters (incomplete files), 1991-2008 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Organizational information and history, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Out awards, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Press releases, 1990-2005 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Queer prom (flyers, tickets), undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Rainbow room (flyers), 2002 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Scholarship information (incomplete file), 2001-2008 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Survey regarding lesbian health concerns, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Transgender (programs supporting health of), 2000-2007 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Transgender lives conference (program), April 14, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Twentieth anniversary celebration (correspondence, flyers, invitations), February 2-28, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Volunteers (applications, orientation, recognition, surveys, forms), 1991-2005 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Women and AIDS (informational material), 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Women (programs supporting health of), 1993-2006 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Women's Health Summit, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Your Turf (flyers and information), 1986-1998 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - YWCA ninth annual comedy night (program), October 11, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Community Center Project - letter of support, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Letter of Agreement HIV/AIDS Risk Reduction Program and the Urban League, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Youth Initiative Grant Proposal, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Continuation of case management services for men and women living with HIV/AIDS, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Letter of support to get funding for services for people in recovery from chemical addiction, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Various grant proposals, including Ryan White grant program, 2000-2004 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Sponsorship of Connecticut PRIDE Festival, 1992-2001 (Box 4)
    - Photos - Gay PRIDE festival planning, 1994-1997 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1992 Invoices (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 1992 Bank Statements (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1992 Income (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1993 Bank Statements (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1993 Deposits (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1993 Receipts (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - 1993 Correspondence [related to Connecticut PRIDE] (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - 1993 Program book and registration [relating to Connecticut PRIDE festival] (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - 1994 Miscellaneous correspondence [relating to Connecticut PRIDE festival] (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - 1994 Receipts (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - 1994 Income (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - 1994 Bank Statements (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - 1994 Miscellaneous correspondence [relating to Connecticut PRIDE] (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - 1994 Program book planning (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - 1994 Correspondence [relating to Connecticut PRIDE] (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - 1994-5 Minutes of meetings, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Connecticut PRIDE membership lists, 1994-1997 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - 1995 Program book planning (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - 1995 Connecticut Gay PRIDE festival planning (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - 1995 Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE Festival program book planning (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - 1996 Connecticut PRIDE Festival planning (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - 1997 Metroline [relating to Connecticut PRIDE] (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - 1997 Connecticut PRIDE Festival planning meeting minutes, October 3, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - 1997 Connecticut PRIDE Committee By Laws, October 19, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - 1999 Correspondence and notes [relating to Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE Festival planning] (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Gay pride festivals [flyers and brochures], 1999 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - 1999 Newspaper articles and ads [relating to Gay pride festivities] (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - 2000 Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE festival planning (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Hartford Courant section B September 23, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 29)